I have spent the last years
لقد أمضيت السنوات الأخيرة
trying to resolve two enigmas:
في محاولة إيجاد حل لمعضلتين:
Why is productivity so disappointing
لماذا الإنتاجية مخيبة للآمل إلى هذا الحد
in all the companies where I work?
في كل الشركات التي أعمل بها؟
I have worked with more than 500 companies.
لقد عملت مع أكثر من 500 شركة.
Despite all the technological advances --
بالرغم من كل التطورات التقنية --
computers, I.T., communications, telecommunications,
الكمبيوترات، النظم المعلوماتية، الاتصالات، الاتصالات عن بعد،
the Internet.
الإنترنت.
Enigma number two:
المعضلة الثانية هي:
Why is there so little engagement at work?
لماذا هناك القليل جداً من التفاعل في العمل؟
Why do people feel so miserable,
لماذا يشعر الناس بالتعاسة البالغة،
even actively disengaged?
و بعدم المشاركة المتعمّد؟
Disengaging their colleagues.
فهم لا يشاركون زملاءهم.
Acting against the interest of their company.
و هم يتصرفون بما لا يصب في مصلحة شركتهم.
Despite all the affiliation events,
بالرغم من كل الأنشطة التي تعزز الانتماء،
the celebration, the people initiatives,
الإحتفالات، مبادرات الناس،
the leadership development programs to train
برامج تطوير القيادة لتدريب
managers on how to better motivate their teams.
المدراء على تحفيز مجموعاتهم بشكل أفضل.
At the beginning, I thought there was
في البداية، ظننت أنه هناك
a chicken and egg issue:
قضية البيضة و الدجاجة هنا:
Because people are less engaged, they are less productive.
لأن الناس تشارك بشكل أقل، فهي تنتج بشكل أقل.
Or vice versa, because they are less productive,
أو العكس صحيح، بسبب انخفاض الإنتاجية،
we put more pressure and they are less engaged.
فنحن نضغط عليهم و بالتالي تقل مشاركتهم.
But as we were doing our analysis
لكن بينما كنا نقوم بتحليلنا
we realized that there was a common root cause
أدركنا أنه هناك سبب أساسي مشترك
to these two issues
لهاتين القضيتين
that relates, in fact, to the basic pillars of management.
و هو في الحقيقة متعلق بالركائز الأساسية للإدارة.
The way we organize is based on two pillars.
تعتمد الطريقة التي ننظم بها على ركيزتين أساسيتين.
The hard -- structure, processes, systems.
القاسية -- التركيب، العمليات، الأنظمة.
The soft --
المرنة --
feelings, sentiments, interpersonal relationships, traits, personality.
المشاعر، العواطف، العلاقات الشخصية، الصفات، الشخصيات.
And whenever a company
و حينما تقوم شركة
reorganizes, restructures, reengineers,
بإعادة ترتيب، إعادة هيكلة، إعادة هندسة،
goes through a cultural transformation program,
فإنها تمر خلال برنامج تحول ثقافي،
it chooses these two pillars.
إنها تختار هاتين الركيزتين.
Now, we try to refine them,
الآن، نحن نحاول صقلهم،
we try to combine them.
و نحاول دمجهم.
The real issue is --
المشكلة الحقيقية هي --
and this is the answer to the two enigmas --
و هذا هو حل المعضلتين --
these pillars are obsolete.
أن هاتين الركيزتين أصبحتا باليتين.
Everything you read in business books is based
يعتمد كل ما تقرأه في كتب إدارة الأعمال
either on one or the other
على أحدهما أو الآخر
or their combination.
أو على توليفة من الإثنين معاً.
They are obsolete.
لقد انتهى عهدهما.
How do they work
كيف لهما أن يصمدا
when you try to use these approaches
عندما تحاول استخدام هذه الطرق
in front of the new complexity of business?
بمواجهة التعقيد الجديد في الأعمال التجارية؟
The hard approach, basically is that you start from strategy,
إن الأسلوب القاسي يعني، أنك تنطلق من التخطيط،
requirements, structures, processes, systems, KPIs, scorecards,
المتطلبات، التراكيب، العمليات، النظم، مؤشرات الأداء الأساسي، بطاقات التقييم،
committees, headquarters, hubs, clusters,
اللجان، المقار، المحاور، التجمعات،
you name it.
سمها ما شئت.
I forgot all the metrics, incentives, committees, middle offices and interfaces.
لقد نسيت كل من المصفوفات، الحوافز، اللجان، المكاتب الوسطى و الواجهات.
What happens basically on the left,
ما الذي يحدث فعلاً من الناحية الأخرى،
you have more complexity, the new complexity of business.
هو أن لديك تعقيد أكثر، التعقيد الجديد في الأعمال التجارية.
We need quality, cost, reliability, speed.
نحن نحتاج إلى الجودة، التكلفة، الموثوقية، السرعة.
And every time there is a new requirement,
و في كل مرة يظهر متطلب جديد،
we use the same approach.
نستخدم نفس الأساليب.
We create dedicated structure processed systems,
نحن نخلق أنظمة معالجة ذات تركيب محدد،
basically to deal with the new complexity of business.
بشكل رئيسي للتعامل مع التعقيد للجديد للأعمال التجارية.
The hard approach creates just complicatedness
إن الأسلوب القاسي يؤدي إلى التعقيد و حسب
in the organization.
في التنظيم.
Let's take an example.
دعنا نأخذ مثال.
An automotive company, the engineering division
في شركة سيارات، يتكون القسم الهندسي
is a five-dimensional matrix.
من مصفوفة ذي خمسة أبعاد.
If you open any cell of the matrix,
إذا فتحت أي خلية من المصفوفة،
you find another 20-dimensional matrix.
تجد مصفوفة أخرى ذو 20 بعد.
You have Mr. Noise, Mr. Petrol Consumption,
لديك الأستاذ. الضجيج، الأستاذ. استهلاك الوقود،
Mr. Anti-Collision Properties.
الأستاذ. الخواص المضادة للاصطدام.
For any new requirement,
لأي متطلب جديد،
you have a dedicated function
لديك دالة محددة
in charge of aligning engineers against
مسؤولة عن توجيه المهندسين إلى
the new requirement.
المتطلب الجديد.
What happens when the new requirement emerges?
ماذا يحدث عندما يبرز المتطلب الجديد؟
Some years ago, a new requirement
قبل بضعة سنوات، ظهر متطلب
appeared on the marketplace:
جديد في ساحة السوق:
the length of the warranty period.
طول مدة الكفالة.
So therefore the new requirement is repairability,
فإذاً المتطلب الجديد هو القابلية للتصليح،
making cars easy to repair.
جعل السيارات سهلة التصليح.
Otherwise when you bring the car to the garage to fix the light,
و إلّا عندما تحضر السيارة إلى الكراج لتصليح الضوء،
if you have to remove the engine
إن كان عليك أن تخرج المحرك
to access the lights,
للوصول إلى الأضواء،
the car will have to stay one week in the garage
فإنه سوف يكون عليك أن تُبقي السيارة في الكراج لمدة أسبوع
instead of two hours, and the warranty budget will explode.
بدلاً من ساعتين، و سوف تتضخم ميزانية الكفالة.
So, what was the solution using the hard approach?
لذا، ما الحل باستخدام الأسلوب القاسي؟
If repairability is the new requirement,
إن كانت القابلية للتصليح هي المتطلب الجديد،
the solution is to create a new function,
فإذاً الحل هو بخلق دور جديد،
Mr. Repairability.
الأستاذ. القابلية للتصليح.
And Mr. Repairability creates the repairability process.
و يقوم الأستاذ. القابلية للتصليح بعملية التصليح.
With a repairability scorecard, with a repairability metric
مع وجود بطاقة تقييم، و مصفوفة
and eventually repairability incentive.
و بالنهاية حافز للقابلية للتصليح .
That came on top of 25 other KPIs.
هذا يأتي علاوة على 25 مؤشر أداء أساسي أخر.
What percentage of these people is variable compensation?
ما النسبة التي يشكلها هؤلاء الناس التي تعد تعويض متغير؟
Twenty percent at most, divided by 26 KPIs,
على الأكثر 20 بالمئة، مقسمة على 26 مؤشر أداء أساسي،
repairability makes a difference of 0.8 percent.
تشكل القابلية للتصليح فرق مقداره 0.8 بالمئة.
What difference did it make in their actions,
ما الاختلاف الذي أدته في أفعالهم،
their choices to simplify? Zero.
خيارهم للتبسيط؟ صفر.
But what occurs for zero impact? Mr. Repairability, process,
لكن ماذا يحدث لأثر مقداره صفر؟ أن يمتلك الأستاذ. القابلية للتصليح، العملية،
scorecard, evaluation, coordination with the 25 other coordinators
بطاقة التقييم، التقييم، التنسيق مع المنسقين ال 25 الآخرين
to have zero impact.
أثر مقداره صفر.
Now, in front of the new complexity of business,
الآن، في مواجهة التعقيد الجديد للأعمال التجارية،
the only solution is not drawing boxes
إن الحل الوحيد ليس في رسم جداول
with reporting lines.
مع سطور الإبلاغ.
It is basically the interplay.
إنه فعلياً بالتفاعلات.
How the parts work together.
كيف تعمل المسارات مع بعضها البعض.
The connections, the interactions, the synapses.
العلاقات، التفاعلات، نقاط الاشتباك العصبي.
It is not the skeleton of boxes, it is the nervous system
إنها ليست الهيكل العظمي للجداول، بل هي الجهاز العصبي
of adaptiveness and intelligence.
للتكيف و الذكاء.
You know, you could call it cooperation, basically.
أتعلم، يمكنك أن تسميه بالتعاون، بشكل رئيسي.
Whenever people cooperate,
حينما يتعاون الناس،
they use less resources. In everything.
فإنهم يستهلكون موارد أقل. في كل النواحي.
You know, the repairability issue
أتعلم، إن قضية القابلية للإصلاح
is a cooperation problem.
هي قضية تعاون.
When you design cars, please take into account
عندما تصمم سيارات، أرجو الأخذ بعين الاعتبار
the needs of those who will repair the cars
حاجات هؤلاء الذين سوف يصلحون السيارات
in the after sales garages.
في كراجات خدمة ما بعد البيع.
When we don't cooperate we need more time,
عندما لا نتعاون نحن نحتاج إلى وقت أطول،
more equipment, more systems, more teams.
معدات أكثر، أنظمة أكثر، فِرَق أكثر.
We need -- When procurement, supply chain, manufacturing don't cooperate
نحن نحتاج -- عندما لا يتعاون قسم المشتريات، و سلسلة التوريد، و التصنيع
we need more stock, more inventories, more working capital.
نحن بحاجة الى مزيد من المخزون، والمزيد من الجَرد، المزيد من رأس المال التشغيل.
Who will pay for that?
من سوف يدفع لذلك؟
Shareholders? Customers?
المستثمرين؟ الزبائن؟
No, they will refuse.
لا، سوف يرفضوا.
So who is left? The employees,
إذاً من بقي؟ الموظفين،
who have to compensate through their super
المجبرين على تعويض النقص في التعاون
individual efforts for the lack of cooperation.
من خلال جهودهم الفردية الجبارة.
Stress, burnout, they are overwhelmed, accidents.
الإجهاد، الإرهاق، إنهم منهكون -- الحوادث.
No wonder they disengage.
لا عجب أنهم لا يتفاعلون.
How do the hard and the soft try to foster cooperation?
كيف تحاول الأساليب القاسية و المرنة تعزيز التعاون؟
The hard: In banks, when there is a problem
القاسية: في البنوك، عندما يكون هناك مشكلة
between the back office and the front office,
بين المكتب الخلفي و المكتب الأمامي،
they don't cooperate. What is the solution?
فإنهم لا يتعاونون. ما هو الحل؟
They create a middle office.
الحل في إنشاء مكتب أوسط.
What happens one year later?
ماذا يحدث بعد سنة لاحقاً؟
Instead of one problem between the back and the front,
بدلاً من مشكلة واحدة بين المكتبين الأمامي و الخلفي،
now I have two problems.
الآن لديَّ مشكلتان.
Between the back and the middle
بين الخلفي و الأوسط
and between the middle and the front.
و بين الأوسط و الأمامي.
Plus I have to pay for the middle office.
بالإضافة إلى ذلك، يجب عليّ أن أدفع للمكتب الأوسط.
The hard approach is unable to foster cooperation.
إن الطريقة القاسية غير قادرة على تعزيز التعاون.
It can only add new boxes, new bones in the skeleton.
هي فقط تضيف جداول جديدة، عظام جديدة إلى الهيكل العظمي.
The soft approach:
أما في الأسلوب المرن:
To make people cooperate, we need to make them like each other.
نحن نجعل الناس تتعاون، يجب أن نجعلهم بحبون بعضهم البعض.
Improve interpersonal feelings,
أن نحسِّن المشاعر بين الأفراد،
the more people like each other, the more they will cooperate.
كلما أحب الناس بعضهم البعض، كلما تعاونوا أكثر.
It is totally wrong.
هذه الفكرة خاطئة كلياً.
It is even counterproductive.
إنها حتى ضد الإنتاجية.
Look, at home I have two TVs. Why?
انظر، في البيت لدي تلفازين. لماذا؟
Precisely not to have to cooperate with my wife.
كي لا أضطر إلى التعاون مع زوجتي تحديداً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Not to have to impose tradeoffs to my wife.
كي لا أفرض تنازلات على زوجتي.
And why I try not to impose tradeoffs to my wife
و السبب في أني لا أحاول فرض التنازلات على زوجتي
is precisely because I love my wife.
هو أنني أحبها.
If I didn't love my wife, one TV would be enough:
إن لم أحبها، لكان تلفاز واحد يكفي:
You will watch my favorite football game,
&amp;quot;سوف تشاهدي مباراة كرة القدم التي لدي،
if you are not happy, how is the book or the door?
و إن لم تكوني سعيدة، أخبريني كيف هو حال الكتاب أو الباب؟&amp;quot;
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The more we like each other,
كلما أحب بعضنا الآخر،
the more we avoid the real cooperation
كلما تجنبنا التعاون الحقيقي
that would strain our relationships by imposing tough tradeoffs.
هذا من شأنه أن يجهد علاقاتنا بفرض تنازلات صعبة.
And we go for a second TV or we escalate
و نحن إما نختار أن يكون لدينا تلفاز آخر أو نصعّد
the decision above for arbitration.
القرار السابق للتحكيم.
Definitely, these approaches are obsolete.
بالطبع، هذه الطرق بالية.
To deal with complexity, to enhance the nervous system,
لذا للتعامل مع التعقيد، لتحسين نظام جديد،
we have created what we call the smart simplicity approach
فقد أنشأنا ما نسميه بأسلوب البساطة الذكية
based on simple rules.
المرتكز على قواعد بسيطة.
Simple rule number one:
القاعد البسيطة الأولى:
Understand what others do.
افهم ما الذي يقوم به الناس الآخرين.
What is their real work?
ما هو عملهم الفعلي؟
We need to go beyond the boxes,
نحن بحاجة إلى تخطي الجداول،
the job descriptions, beyond the surface
و توصيف الوظائف، إلى ما وراء ظاهر
of the container, to understand the real content.
الوعاء، لنفهم المحتوى الحقيقي.
Me, designer, if I put a wire here,
أنا، المصمم، إن وضعت سلك هنا،
I know that it will mean that we will have to
فإنني أعلم أن ذلك يعني أنه سوف يكون علينا
remove the engine to access the lights.
إزالة المحرك للوصول إلى الأضواء.
Second, you need to reenforce integrators.
ثانياً، يجب عليك أن تعزز عوامل التوحّد.
Integrators are not middle offices, they are managers,
عوامل التوحد ليست مكاتب وسطى، بل هي المدراء،
existing managers that you reinforce
تعزيز المدراء الموجودين أصلاً
so that they have power and interest
لكي يكون لديهم السلطة و الاهتمام
to make others cooperate.
بجعل الآخرين يتعاونوا.
How can you reinforce your managers as integrators?
كيف يمكنك تمكين مدراءك كعوامل توحد؟
By removing layers.
عن طريق إزالة الطبقات.
When there are too many layers
عندما يكون هناك طبقات كثيرة
people are too far from the action,
فإن الناس تكون بعيدة جداً عن التنفيذ،
therefore they need KPIs, metrics,
و هنا تأتي الحاجة إلى مؤشرات الأداء الأساسي، المصفوفات،
they need poor proxies for reality.
إنهم بحاجة إلى ممثل سيئ للحقيقة.
They don't understand reality
إنهم لا يفهمون الحقيقة.
and they add the complicatedness of metrics, KPIs.
و هي تزيد من تعقيد مصفوفات مؤشرات الأداء الأساسي.
By removing rules -- the bigger we are,
بإزالة القواعد -- كلما زادت مكانتنا،
the more we need integrators,
كلما زادت حاجتنا إلى عوامل التوحد،
therefore the less rules we must have,
لذا يجب أن يكون لدينا قوانين أقل،
to give discretionary power to managers.
لإعطاء سلطة اتخاذ القرارات التقديرية للمدراء.
And we do the opposite --
و نحن نفعل العكس --
the bigger we are, the more rules we create.
كلما زادت مكانتنا، كلما زادت القوانين التي نضعها.
And we end up with the Encyclopedia Britannica of rules.
و ينتهي بنا المطاف بوضعنا للموسوعة بريتانيكا (البريطانية) للقوانين.
You need to increase the quanitity of power
يجب أن تزيد من مقدار السلطة
so that you can empower everybody
كي تستطيع منحها للجميع
to use their judgment, their intelligence.
ليستخدموا تحكيمهم، ذكاءهم.
You must give more cards to people
يجب أن تعطي بطاقات أكثر للناس
so that they have the critical mass of cards
لكي يصبح لديهم الكمية المناسبة
to take the risk to cooperate,
كي يجرؤوا على التعاون،
to move out of insulation.
ليخرجوا من العزلة.
Otherwise, they will withdraw. They will disengage.
و إلّا، فهم سوف ينسحبوا. سوف يعزفوا عن المشاركة.
These rules, they come from game theory
ثلاثة قواعد، مستوحاة من نظرية الألعاب
and organizational sociology.
و علم الإجتماع التنظيمي.
You can increase the shadow of the future.
أنت تستطيع زيادة الخوف من المستقبل.
Create feedback loops that expose people
تستطيع خلق ردة فعل تفضح الناس
to the consequences of their actions.
نتيجة لأفعالهم.
This is what the automotive company did
هذا ما فعلته شركة السيارات
when they saw that Mr. Repairability had no impact.
عندما رأوا أنه لا يوجد تأثير للأستاذ. القابلية للتصليح
They said to the design engineers:
قالوا لمهندسي التصميم:
Now, in three years, when the new car is launched on the market,
&amp;quot;الآن، خلال ثلاثة سنوات، عند إطلاق السيارة الجديدة في السوق،
you will move to the after sales network, and become in charge
سوف يتم نقلك لشبكة ما بعد البيع، و سوف تصبح المسؤول
of the warranty budget,
عن ميزانية الكفالة،
and if the warranty budget explodes,
و إن تضخمت ميزانية الكفالة حتى الانفجار،
it will explode in your face. (Laughter)
فسوف تنفجر في وجهك.&amp;quot; (ضحك)
Much more powerful than 0.8 percent variable compensation.
ذلك أقوى بكثير من 0.8 بالمئة من التعويض المتغير.
You need also to increase reciprocity,
أنت أيضاً بحاجة إلى زيادة التبادلية،
by removing the buffers that make us self-sufficient.
بإزالة مخففات الصدمات التي تجعلنا مكتفيين ذاتياً.
When you remove these buffers,
عندما تزيلها،
you hold me by the nose, I hold you by the ear.
يصبح الأمر إن مسكتني من الأنف، سوف أمسكك من الأذن.
We will cooperate.
سوف نتعاون.
Remove the second TV.
أزل التلفاز الثاني.
There are many second TVs at work
هناك الكثير من أجهزة التلفاز الثانية في العمل
that don't create value,
التي لا تضيف أي قيمة،
they just provide dysfunctional self-sufficiency.
هي فقط تؤدي إلى اكتفاء ذاتي معيوب.
You need to reward those who cooperate
أنت بحاجة إلى مكافأة هؤلاء الذين يتعاونون
and blame those who don't cooperate.
و تعاتب هؤلاء الذين لا يتعاونون.
The CEO of The Lego Group,
إن المدير التنفيذي لمجموعة ليجو،
Jorgen Vig Knudstorp, has a great way to use it.
جورجن فيج كندستورب، لديه طريقة رائعة لاستخدامها.
He says, blame is not for failure,
يقول: &amp;quot;إن العتاب ليس على الفشل،
it is for failing to help or ask for help.
إنما هو على عدم القيام بالمساعدة أو طلب المساعدة.&amp;quot;
It changes everything.
إنه يغير كل شيء.
Suddenly it becomes in my interest to be transparent
فجأة يصبح من مصلحتي أن أكون شفافاً
on my real weaknesses, my real forecast,
من ناحية نقاط ضعفي الحقيقية، توقعاتي الحقيقية،
because I know I will not be blamed if I fail,
لأني أعلم أنني لن أٌلام إن فشلت،
but if I fail to help or ask for help.
لكن الأمر مختلف إن فشلت في المساعدة أو طلب المساعدة.
When you do this, it has a lot of implications
لفعل ذلك، آثار عديدة
on organizational design.
على التصميم التنظيمي.
You stop drawing boxes, dotted lines, full lines;
فإنك تتوقف عن رسم الجداول، السطور النقطية، السطور الكاملة:
you look at their interplay.
سوف تنظر إلى تفاعلها.
It has a lot of implications on financial policies
لذلك أيضاً العديد من الأثار على السياسات المالية
that we use.
التي نستخدمها.
On human resource management practices.
و على ممارساتنا في إدارة الموارد البشرية.
When you do that, you can manage complexity,
عندما تفعل ذلك بإمكانك إدارة التعقيد،
the new complexity of business,
التعقيد الجديد للأعمال التجارية،
without getting complicated.
دون أن تتعقد.
You create more value with lower cost.
سوف تخلق قيمة عالية بتكلفة أقل.
You simultaneously improve performance and satisfaction at work
و في نفس الوقت سوف تحسّن الأداء و الرضا في العمل
because you have removed the common root cause
لأنك قد أزلت السبب الرئيسي
that hinders both.
الذي يعطل تعقيدات الاثنين.
The real battle is not against competitors.
إن المعركة الحقيقية ليست ضد المنافسين.
This is rubbish, very abstract.
هذا سخيف، إنه فكر تجريدي جداً.
When do we meet competitors to fight them?
أين نقابل المنافسين لنتقاتل معهم؟
The real battle is against ourselves,
إن المعركة الحقيقية هي ضد أنفسنا،
against our bureaucracy, our complicatedness.
ضد روتيننا، تعقيدنا.
Only you can fight, can do it.
أنت وحدك القادر على القتال، على النجاح.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)